Xavier University inactive committees records
Xavier University Archives and Special Collections
Xavier University inactive committees records
1937-2006
Xavier University Archives and Special Collections Phone: 513-745-4821 http://www.xavier.edu/cm/archives
Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio)
1.25 linear feet (3 boxes)
This is a collection of committee records of various inactive Xavier University committees. Holdings for individual committees may be fragmented.
XUA-36
History of Xavier University inactive committee records
This is a collection of records from various lesser known discontinued committees at Xavier University. Holdings for individual committees may be limited and fragmented.
Scope and Content
This is a collection of inactive Xavier University committee records. The collection includes records for both ad hoc and standing committees. A number of topics are represented in the assembled documents which are arranged alphabetically by committee name.
Statement of Arrangement
Records are arranged alphabetically by committee name.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Subjects:
Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio)--Administration; Track system (Education)--Ohio; Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio)--Planning; Universities and colleges--Curricula--Catalogs; Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio)--Societies; Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio)--Curricula; Multiculturalism--Ohio; African Americans--Education (Higher)--Ohio; Campus planning--Ohio; Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio)--Buildings; Arts--Ohio; Language and languages--Study and teaching; Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio)--Funds and scholarships; Universities and colleges--Honors courses--Ohio; Education--Aims and objectives--Ohio; Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio)--Finance; Students--Civil rights--Ohio; Xavier University (Cincinnati,Ohio)--Students; Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio)--Libraries; Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio)--Employees; Competency-based education--Ohio; Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio)--Public relations; Student publications--Ohio; Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio)--Research grants; Research--Ohio; Schedules, School--Ohio; Military art and science--Ohio; United States--Army--Reserve Officers' Training Corps; College students; Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio)--Tuition
Organizations/Corporations:
Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Administrative Committee; Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Advanced Placement Committee; Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Alumni Council; Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). University Catalogue Committee; Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Coordinating Committee; Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Council of the College of Arts and Sciences; Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Diversity Advisory Committee; Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Edgecliff Campus Coordinating Committee; Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Facilities Planning Committee; Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Fine Arts Committee; Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Committee on Foreign Languages in the Xavier Core; Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Graduate Scholarship and Fellowship Advisory Committee; Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Honors Programs Review Committee; Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Committee on Instructional Purposes; Xavier University (Cincinnati,Ohio). Interim Executive Academic Committee; Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Investment Counseling Committee; Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Joint Statement Committee; Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Library Planning Committee; Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Non-Faculty Salary Committee; Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Outcomes Assessment Committee; Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). University Planning Committee; Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Planning Steering Committee; Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Public Relations Committee; Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Student Publications Committee; Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Committee on Research and Advanced Study; Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Schedule Committee; Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Speakers and Programs Committee; Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Academic Council. ROTC Subcommittee; Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Committee on the Statutes; Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Committee on the Study of Academic and Social Life at Xavier; Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Committee on Tuition; Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Committee on University Purposes
Detailed Description of The Collection
- Administrative Committee, 1967-1986 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  It is not clear when this committee was created, but it existed during the 1961-62 Academic Year.
  Normally it met every Monday morning during the school year and was sometimes referred to as the Monday Morning Administrators' Meeting. Its name was changed several times over the years and it was discontinued after the meeting of September 25, 1986. Prior to 1975 it was called the Administrative Problems Committee. From 1975 to 1977, it was known as the Administrative Communication Committee. From 1977 to 1986, it In 1971-72 the committee was described as follows: "The Administrative Problems Committee, appointed and chaired by the president, meets weekly during the school year. Its purpose is to facilitate communication between the various administrative offices of the University. Its membership includes the principal University administrators and a representative of the Faculty Committee." In 1977-78 it was described as follows: "The Administrative Committee is chaired by the president. Consisting of major administrators, a representative of the Faculty Committee and the president of the Student Government, the committee facilitates general communication between the various offices and divisions of the University."
- Advanced Placement Committee, 1968-1974 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  In 1961 Xavier had an Advanced Placement Committee. It is not known how long the Committee had existed before that. The Committee continued in existence until the end of the 1974-75 Academic Year, when it was apparently discontinued. After that year it no longer appears on the list of the University's standing committees.
  The charge of the committee was as follows: "The Advanced Placement Committee makes recommendations to the Academic Vice President on policies and programs involving the advanced ranking of students wishing to enter the University. Its members include representatives of the academic department which sponsor advanced programs." (See "Descriptions of the XU Committees, 1974-75").
- Alumni Council, 1974-1984 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  The history of this council is obscure. There is no mention of it in any of the annual lists of the University's Standing Committees available in the archives.
  The first memo in this collection, written by James W. Sassen and dated September 5, 1975, indicates that the Council was created in the fall of 1975. It is not clear when it went out of existence. The charge of the Council is not clear. In president Charles Currie's memo to the members of the Alumni Council dated March 29, 1984, he says that the purpose of each of the Council's subcommittees is "to review what is happening in a particular area (of the University) and to offer advice, criticism and suggestions."
- Catalogue Committee, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  It is not certain when this committee was first created or when it went out of existence. It seems never to have appeared on the annual list of the university's standing committees.
  It met several times in 1966-67 and the minutes of two of those meetings are the only record we have of its existence. The committees' purpose was to revise, correct and update the University course catalogue from year to year.
- Coordinating Committee, 1937-1942 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  In a letter he wrote on June 5, 1937, Edward VonderHaar, Xavier's Director of Publicity, speaks of the Coordinating Committee as having just been created. It seems to have been discontinued during the Second World War and was not revived afterwards.
  It was made up of representatives of the organizations affiliated with Xavier University and St. Xavier High School. At one point, it was suggested that the Jesuit Retreat League be asked to join. This does not seem to have happened. According to its constitution the object of the committee "shall be to bring together the various associations affiliated with Xavier University and St. Xavier High School for mutual cooperation and the more effective furthering of activities inaugurated by one or more of the several associations the better to promote Jesuit education." In particular, the committee was to prevent conflicts in the scheduling of activities and events. Its members were drawn from friends, alums and administrators of both institutions.
- Council of the College of Arts and Sciences, 1973-1975 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  The Council of the College of Arts and Sciences was created at the beginning of the 1972-73 academic year and was discontinued at the end of the 1980-81 academic year.
  Its official name was the Council of the College of Arts and Sciences, but was occasionally referred as the Arts and Sciences Council - Planning Board. The committee's charge in 1973-74 was: "...The purpose of the Council is to study new courses and programs proposed by various departments, to encourage inter-departmental cooperation, and to initiate changes in curriculum." In 1980-81, the charge read: "Included in its responsibilities are the study of new programs and the development of new curricula. The chair of the Council is the Dean."
- Diversity Advisory Committee, 2003 July 31 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  The Diversity Advisory Committee was created by President Michael J. Graham, S.J. probably sometime in 2002. It submitted is final report on July 31, 2003.
  Dr. Kenneth B. Durgans and Dr. Janice Walker served as co-chairs. The committee was created to "develop a comprehensive plan for Xavier University which will establish promoting diversity as a core value of the institution....recommend implementation of strategies created by the Diversity Advisory Committee....focus immediate efforts on issues pertaining to the number and participation of African Americans and African Diaspora in the Xavier University community which includes all internal and external constituents....routinely evaluate components of the plan and related strategies based upon that evaluation and then revise the plan and strategies accordingly." (Committee's Final Report)
- Edgecliff Campus Coordinating Committee, 1984-1986 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Originally known as the Edgecliff Committee, this committee was created in July, 1984. It ceased to exist sometime after February, 1986, when Xavier sold the Edgecliff property.
  It had several different names in the course of its history, but the Edgecliff Campus Coordinating Committee was the most common. In 1985-86, the annual list of committees described the charge of the committee as follows: "The purpose of this committee is to insure that articulation and communication between the Edgecliff and Avondale campuses remains effective and that the specific needs of the Edgecliff Campus are responded to." The committee was divided into two parts, the Operations subcommittee and the Policy subcommittee.
- Facilities Planning Committee, 1986-1988 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  At a meeting which it held on November 26, 1986, the Executive Committee decided that the responsibilities of the Rainbo Task Force should be broadened and that the committee should be renamed the Facilities Planning Committee.
  Dr. Richard Hirte', the Vice President of Financial Administration, was appointed first chair. The committee was discontinued sometime around 2005. According to a memo from President Albert DiUlio, S.J., to Dr. Robert Murray, dated December 2, 1986, "The first charge of the Facilities Planning Committee is twofold: 1. To assess the existing time and space resources on the Xavier campus (excluding the Rainbo property). 2. To develop a short-term contingency plan to fully utilize existing resources to accommodate a move of all course offerings and personnel from the Edgecliff campus to the Xavier campus by summer, 1987. As of 2001-02, the committee's charge was as follows: "The Facilities Planning Committee assists the President with major University facility planning by identifying space and facility needs, locating resources, and recommending alternative solutions."
- Fine Arts Committee, 1950-1959 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  According to the annual University Lists of Standing Committees, the Fine Arts Committee was created sometime prior to 1961 and was discontinued at the end of the 1968-69 academic year. It was reinstated at the beginning of the 1972-73 school year and was permanently dropped after the 1983-84 year. In 1973-74 the charge read as follows: "Appointed annually by the President and electing its own chairman, the Fine Arts Committee makes recommendations to the Vice President for Student Development on fine arts programs and exhibitions." In 1980-81 the charge read as follows: "This committee has as its purpose to develop interest in the fine arts in the community and to draw up recommendations regarding fine arts, the Carriage House Gallery, art exhibits, the care, storing and sale of paintings and other artistic objects belonging to the University." (Annual Lists of University Standing Committees)
- Foreign Languages in the Xavier Core Ad Hoc Committee, 1979 February-June (Box 1, Folder 11)
  In early 1979, the Board of Undergraduate Studies instructed the dean of the College of Arts and Sciences, Joseph T. Angilella, S.J., to form an ad hoc committee to study the role of foreign languages in the core curriculum at Xavier.
  The committee, chaired by Dr. Karl Wentersdorf, professor of English, consisted of four faculty members and one student. It began its deliberations in February, 1979, and submitted its final report in June of that same year. The report was then delivered to the Board of Undergraduate Studies for its review on August 13, 1979. The charge of the committee was "to study the role of foreign languages in the core curriculum at Xavier." (See the 8/13/1979 memo of committee members to the academic administrators.)
- Graduate Scholarship and Fellowship Advisory Committee, 1956-1973 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  This committee was in existence in 1963 under the title of the Graduate Scholarship Advisory Committee. However, it first appeared on the annual list of the University standing committees in 1966-67 under the name of the Graduate Scholarship and Fellowship Advisory Committee.
  The committee was discontinued at the end of the 1975-76 academic year. According to the annual list of standing committees for 1971-72, the charge of this committee was as follows: "The Committee on Graduate Scholarships and Fellowships, appointed annually by the Provost, Robert Mulligan, S.J., makes recommendations to the undergraduate deans and to the Academic Vice President as to the manner in which Xavier undergraduates may be best assisted in obtaining scholarships and fellowships for graduate work."
- Honors Program Review Committee, 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  This ad hoc committee was created by the Academic Vice President, Dr. Joan Connell, in March, 1991.
  For a list of the persons who served on it, see page 1 of the final report. The committee met for the last time on May 7, 1992, when it unanimously approved its final report. The final report was then published on May 19, 1992. The committee was charged with the task of reviewing the Honors Programs at Xavier University and make recommendations concerning them. At the time, there were two Honors Programs, the Honors Bachelor of Arts Program and the University Scholars' Program. For further information concerning the committee's charge, see page 2 of the Final Report.
- Committee on Instructional Purposes, 1955-1959 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  In early March, 1957, President Paul L. O'Connor, S.J., acting on the suggestion of the Academic Council, appointed a committee "to recommend how we can best study the purposes of our instructional program. Eventually we want a full statement of our objectives that will serve to guide curricular decisions and stimulate improvement of instruction." (Memo by Rev. Henry Wirtenberger, S.J., dated March 8, 1957)
  The work of this committee began in March 1957 and ended in March 1959. While this committee functioned independently of Xavier's preparations for the 1958 visitation by the North Central Association, it clearly played a role in Xavier's self-study prior to the visit. The committee is sometimes referred to as Instructional Purposes Committee and sometimes The Evaluation Committee.
- Interim Executive Academic Committee, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  In early August, 1985, Dr. John Minahan resigned from the position of Academic Vice President. To fill this office President Charles Currie, S. J., established the Interim Executive Academic Committee (IEAC) composed of Charles Cusick the Dean of the College of Arts and Sciences, Roger Fortin, Associate Vice President for academic affairs, and Francis Mastrianna, Dean of the College of Business Administration. The triumvirate, or troika, as the IEAC was called, assumed the responsibilities assigned to the office of the Academic Vice President as specified in the XU Faculty Handbook. The Interim Executive Academic Committee was discontinued in the summer of 1986 when Dr. Robert Murray, professor of Classics, was appointed acting Academic Vice President for one year. In June 1987, Dr. Joan Connell became Academic Vice President. (Fortin's history of Xavier, pages 312 to 317) The committee assumed "the responsibilities assigned to the Office of the Academic Vice President in the Faculty Handbook, page 4". (Memo to Faculty and Administration from Charles L. Currie, S. J. dated August 29, 1985.)
- Investment Counseling Committee, 1971 September 15 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  This committee seems to have been created in September, 1971, at the suggestion of Mr. Bert Reynold. It consisted of 8 persons including the president and the financial vice president of the University. It is not known when the committee was discontinued. The following information on the charge of the committee is taken from the minutes of the committee's meeting on September 15, 1971: "For a number of years, Mr. Bert Reynold has on a voluntary basis been acting as an investment counsel to the University. On several occasions he has suggested an advisory committee that would serve as a broader base for policy decisions. The present committee will meet this need. Meeting regularly, it will advise on general policy and, from time to time, individual members would be called upon for advice on particular action".
- Joint Statement Committee (Rights and Freedoms of Students), 1969-1971 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  In 1967 this committee was created to produce a university statement on the rights and freedoms of students at Xavier University. In late July, 1970, the committee submitted a proposed text to President Paul L. O'Connor, S.J., entitled "Joint Statement of Rights and Freedoms of Students for Xavier University". The document was eventually approved by the Board of Trustees. Subsequently, the Joint Statement Committee became a standing committee of the university. The original Joint Statement Committee was charged with the task of writing the Joint Statement of Student Rights and Freedoms. After that, the standing Joint Statement Committee had the "responsibility of regularly reviewing the officially approved University statement on student rights and for proposing additions or emendations to the statement. Its chairman is appointed by the Provost". (Descriptions of Committees, 1971-72). The committee seems to have been discontinued at the end of 1974-75 academic year.
- Library Planning Committee, 2002-2003 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  This committee was created in late 2002 and continued its work until sometime in the middle of 2003 when it apparently went out of existence. It seems to have been an ad hoc committee. In a document dated January 9, 2003 and titled "Library Planning Committee: Project Charter", the committee's goal was "to explain the Library Vision Statement in operational terms". The committee was to "articulate the design and service expectations for Xavier University's library." The ultimate goal was to identify the service and space needs "of a new facility" which will then be interpreted by an architectural design consultant
- Non-Faculty Salary Committee, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  It is not clear when this committee was created or when it was discontinued. It is mentioned in the annual list of the University standing committees for the years 1961-62 and 1964-65, but for no other years. The course catalogues do not mention it at all. The few documents in this collection are dated 1971. There seems to be no other information available about its meetings or business. According to the memo written by Thomas W. Gehner dated April 2, 1971, this committee had the responsibility of reviewing the current salary ranges for all staff employees, and made recommendations to the Board of Trustees concerning the salary ranges for the following year.
- Outcomes Assessment Committee, 1993 June (Box 2, Folder 20)
  The Outcomes Assessment Committee was formed in November, 1991, and met almost weekly during the 1992-93 academic year to develop a plan for assessing student academic achievement at Xavier University. The committee submitted its final report in June, 1993, and went out of existence. For more information on how this committee's recommendations were implemented, consult the archives boxes labeled PLANS FOR ASSESSMENT OF STUDENT ACADEMIC ACHIEVEMENT 1993-2007 FOR THE HIGHER LEARNING COMMISSION OF THE NORTH CENTRAL ASSOCIATION. (3 boxes) Sometime in the late 2000s a new committee named the Academic Assessment and Planning Committee was created and was still listed as a standing committee during the 2013-14 academic year. "The North Central Association's requirement for documentation of student academic achievement reflects a national initiative as public official demand greater accountability from colleges and universities. The Outcomes Assessment Committee, in November, 1991, initiated as eighteen month process of developing a model for assessment of student achievement and quality improvement within the Division of Academic Affairs at Xavier University." (Committee's Final Report, page ii)
- University Planning Committee, 1985 May 1 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  "Building on President Charles Currie's initial planning efforts, in the fall of 1984 the university established a University Planning Committee. Co-chaired by Frank Hoenemeyer of the Board of Trustees and Dr. John Minahan, the Academic Vice President, the committee consisted of administrators, faculty, students, alumni, and friends of the university." The committee completed its work in December, 1984, and submitted its final report sometime in 1985. The committee was "charged to review the strengths, weaknesses, opportunities and threats (SWOT) of each university department." (Fortin's history, page 301)
- Planning Steering Committee All Committee Reports: Integration of the Strategic Plan (Draft), 2003 June (Box 2, Folder 22)
  This folder contains the document "All Committee Reports" of June, 2003. These are the reports of the ten task forces or groups created by the Planning Steering Committee. The document includes the introductory chapter "Integration of the Strategic Plan, June, 2003 (Draft)."